<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Yet another boring programmer's blog</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/About.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2012-10-17T20:00:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Something boring about me</title><link href="/about.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-10-17T20:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Piotr Deszyński</name></author><id>tag:,2012-10-17:about.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Piotr Deszyński&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;placeholder for image ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yup that's me. Or at least there will be me. I'm waiting for some picture that can be used here. But who am I?
Yet another boring programmer, who loves sitting down nearby his computer and dive into different stuff. Sadly (or rather this is my big luck)
I have a wife which doesn't allow me to sit and work too much. So basically I'm always having problem with time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What am I doing?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now I'm working in company named &lt;strong&gt;Red Sky&lt;/strong&gt;. Don't know if you heard about it thought... 
maybe you heard about &lt;a href="http://www.filestube.com," title="Filestube"&gt;Filestube&lt;/a&gt;... Still nothing?
I'm working here mostly on webdevel. Using PHP, Javascript, Python, C++ and sometimes Java. When I have some free time (can say once per month) then
I like to dig into OpenGL(ES) and Android platform.
Besides these I'm interested in code quality (OOP metrics) and design patterns. So if you know any of these mail me (deszynski [at] red-sky.pl)! It'll be a pleasure to
exchange some info.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other thing that I have on my head is recrutation to &lt;strong&gt;Red Sky&lt;/strong&gt; company. So if you would like to send a CV to &lt;a href="mailto:work@red-sky.pl," title="Recrutation"&gt;work@red-sky.pl&lt;/a&gt;,
probably you will meet me there in the room, asking you some questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm playing also as a boss in &lt;strong&gt;Red Sky SRL&lt;/strong&gt; - Moldovan branch of our company, where I spent 1+ year, also trying great Moldovan wine. 
Still I'm not sure if I'm good or bad one (hope seeing comments saying that I'm a good one).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last thing - from few days I'm called in our company &lt;strong&gt;"Culture Ninja"&lt;/strong&gt;, whatever it is. Hope I will be able to be a Ninja enough to maintain this role
and make something good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beneath you will find my certifications:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ups, it's empty for now. After second thought: nope, it will stay empty here even after. I'm not sure if showing off with certs proves anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;TL;DR&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Piotr Deszyński&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Working at &lt;strong&gt;Red Sky Sp. z o.o.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PHP, Python, C++, Java, Zend Framework, jQuery, CSS, HTML5&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code quality (OOP metrics)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interested in: all technologies and programming stuff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><category term="about"></category></entry></feed>